Chapter 93.
The Castaway.
It was but some few days after encountering the Frenchmen that a most
significant event befell the most insignificant of the Peekquad's crew. An
event most lamentable and which ended in providing the sometimes madly merry and
predestinated craft with a living and ever accompanying prophecy of whatever
shattered sequel might prove her own.
Now in the whale ship it is not everyone that goes in the boats. Some few hands
are reserved called shipkeepers, whose province it is to work the vessel while
the boats are pursuing the whale. As a general thing, these shipkeepers are as
hearty fellows as the men comprising the boat's crew. But if there happens to be
an unduly slender, clumsy, or timmerous white in the ship, that white is certain
to be made a shipkeeper. It was so in the Peekquad with the little negro
Pippen by nickname, Pip by abbreviation.
Poor Pip. You have heard of him before.
You must remember his tambourine on that dramatic midnight so gloomy jolly.
In outer aspect, Pip and Doughboy made a match like a black pony and a white one,
of equal developments, though of dissimilar color, driven in one
eccentric span. But while Hapless Doughboy was by nature dull and torpid
in his intellects, Pip, though over tender-hearted, was at bottom very
bright, with that pleasant, genial, jolly brightness peculiar to his tribe,
a tribe which ever enjoy all holidays and festivities, with finer, freer
relish than any other race. For blacks, the year's calendar should show not but
365 Fourth of July and New Year's days.
Nor smile so while I write that this little black was brilliant, for even
blackness has its brilliancancy. Behold yawn lustrous ebony panled in king's
cabinets. But Pip loved life and all life's peaceable securities, so that the
panicstriking business in which he had somehow unaccountably become entrapped
had most sadly blurred his brightness.
Though, as he long will be seen, what was thus temporarily subdued in him, in
the end was destined to be luridly illuminated by strange wild fires that
fictitiously showed him off to 10 times the natural luster with which, in his
native Talin County in Connecticut, he had once enlivened many of Fiddler's
frolic on the green, and at melodious even tide, with his gay haha, had turned
the round horizon into one starbelled tambourine.
So though in the clear air of day, suspended against a blue veined neck,
the pure watered diamond drop will healthful glow, yet when the cunning
jeweler would show you the diamond in its most impressive luster, he lays it
against a gloomy ground, and then lights it up, not by the sun, but by some
unnatural gases. Then come out those fiery eulgences, infernally superb. Then
the evil blazing diamond, once the divinest symbol of the crystal skies,
looks like some crown jewel stolen from the king of hell. But led us to the
story. It came to pass that in the Amberress affair, Stubs after Orsman
chanced so to sprain his hand, as for a time to become quite maimed, and
temporarily Pip was put in his place.
The first time Stub lowered with him, Pip evinced much nervousness, but
happily for that time escaped close contact with the whale, and therefore
came off not altogether discreditably, though Stub, observing him, took care
afterwards to exhort him to cherish his courageousness to the utmost, for he
might often find it needful.
Now upon the second lowering, the boat paddled upon the whale, and as the fish
received the darted iron, it gave its customary wrap, which happened in this
instance to be right under poor Pip's seat. The involuntary consternation of
the moment caused him to leap, paddle in hand, out of the boat, and in such a way
that part of the slack whale line coming against his chest, he breasted it
overboard with him, so as to become entangled in it, when at last plumping
into the water. That instant these stricken whales started on a fierce run.
The line swiftly straightened and presto, poor Pip, came all foaming up to
the chocks of the boat, remorselessly dragged there by the line which had
taken several turns around his chest and neck. Tashego stood in the boughs. He
was full of the fire of the hunt. He hated Pip for a poultrune. Snatching the
boat knife from its sheath, he suspended its sharp edge over the line, and
turning toward Stub, exclaimed interrogatively, "Cut." Meanwhile, Pip's
blue choked face plainly looked, "Do for God's sake." All passed in a flash. In
less than half a minute, this entire thing happened. "Damn him! Cut!" roared
Stub. And so, the whale was lost, and Pip was saved.
So soon as he recovered himself, the poor little negro was assailed by yells
and execrations from the crew. Tranquil permitting these irregular cursings to
evaporate, Stub then, in a plain business-like but still half humorous
manner, cursed Pip officially, and that done unofficially gave him much
wholesome advice. The substance was never jump from a boat, Pip. Except, but
all the rest was indefinite as the soundest advice ever is. Now, in
general, stick to the boat is your true motto in whailing. But cases will
sometimes happen when leap from the boat is still better. Moreover, as if
perceiving at last that if he should give undiluted conscientious advice to
Pip, he would be leaving him too wide a margin to jump in for the future, Stub
suddenly dropped all advice and concluded with a perempter command.
Stick to the boat, Pip, or by the Lord, I won't pick you up if you jump. Mind
that we can't afford to lose whales by the likes of you. A whale would sell for
30 times what you would, Pip, in Alabama. bear that in mind and don't
jump anymore. Hereby perhaps Stub indirectly hinted that though man loved
his fellow, yet man is a money-making animal, which propensity too often
interferes with his benevolence.
But we are all in the hands of the gods," and Pip jumped again. It was
under very similar circumstances to the first performance, but this time he did
not breast out the line, and hence, when the whale started to run, Pip was left
behind on the sea like a hurried traveler's trunk. Alas, Stub was but too
true to his word. It was a beautiful bounteous blue day. The spangled sea
calm and cool and flatly stretching away all round to the horizon like
goldbeater's skin hammered out to the extremist. Bobbing up and down in that
sea. Pip's eban head showed like a head of cloves. No boat knife was lifted when
he fell so rapidly a stern. Stub's inexurable back was turned upon him, and
the whale was winged. In 3 minutes a whole mile of shoreless ocean was
between Pip and Stub. Out of the center of the sea, poor Pip turned his crisp,
curling black head to the sun. Another lonely castaway, though the loftiest and the brightest.
Now in calm weather, to swim in the open ocean is as easy to the practice swimmer
as to ride in a spring carriage ashore.
But the awful lonesomeness is intolerable. The intense concentration
of self in the middle of such a heartless immensity. My God, who can
tell it? Mark how when sailors in a dead calm bathe in the open sea, mark how
closely they hug their ship and only coast along her sides. But had Stub
really abandoned the poor little negro to his fate? No, he did not mean to at
least because there were two boats in his wake, and he supposed no doubt that
they would, of course, come up to Pip very quickly and pick him up, though
indeed such considerations towards oresman jeopardized through their own
timidity, is not always manifested by the hunters in all similar instances,
and such instances not unfrequently occur. Almost invariably in the fishery,
a coward, so-called, is marked with the same ruthless detestation peculiar to
military navies and armies.
But it so happened that those boats, without seeing Pip, suddenly spying
whales close to them on one side, turned and gave chase, and Stub's boat was now
so far away, and he and all his crew so intent upon the fish that Pip's ringed
horizon began to expand around him miserably. By the merest chance, the
ship itself at last rescued him. But from that hour the little negro went
about the deck an idiot. Such at least they said he was. The sea had jeeringly
kept his finite body up, but drowned the infinite of his soul. Not drowned
entirely, though, rather carried down alive to wondrous depths, where strange
shapes of the unwarped primal world glided to and fro before his passive
eyes. and the miser merman wisdom revealed his hoarded heaps. And among
the joyous, heartless, ever juvenile eternities, Pip saw the multitudinous
god omnipresent coral insects that out of the firmament of waters heaved the
colossal orbs. He saw God's foot upon the treddle of the loom and spoke it,
and therefore his shipmates called him mad. So man's insanity is heaven's
sense, and wandering from all mortal reason, man comes at last to that
celestial thought, which to reason is absurd and frantic, and wheel or woe
feels then uncompromised, indifferent as his god.
For the rest, blame not stub too hardly.
The thing is common in that fishery, and in the sequel of the narrative, it will
then be seen what, like abandonment befell myself.